<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: se491 | se2014.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://se2014.com/blog/categories/se491/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://se2014.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-29T12:46:35+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://se2014.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[se2014.com]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I Wish I Knew for the Design Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://se2014.com/blog/2012/04/06/what-i-wish-i-knew-for-the-design-project/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-06T19:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://se2014.com/blog/2012/04/06/what-i-wish-i-knew-for-the-design-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having completed their design projects, the 2012 class of Software
Engineering gave an informal presentation on Thursday to share their
experiences.</p>

<h2>Choosing Groups</h2>

<p><em>The difference between marriage and your group is that you can
divorce a marriage.</em>" -P. Ward</p>

<ul>
<li>Choosing your group is the key step, will be with them for <strong>1.5
years</strong></li>
<li>Similar (interests, work ethic, coding styles, language/framework)

<ul>
<li>"... or you'll be working by yourself, and there <em>will</em> be
unhappiness."</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Technical Electives

<ul>
<li>If enrolled together, your project will stagnate or suffer</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Multiple Approaches

<ul>
<li>Find people you've worked with before, people who you know you can
work with</li>
<li>Defer group formation, have people coalesce around project ideas

<ul>
<li>"Don't be afraid to work with someone you've never worked with
before.'</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>"You don't get to choose who you work with in industry."</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>YMMV: Significant Others

<ul>
<li>"I'm not sure I'd want to work with my wife. You know, seeing the
same person 168 hours a week. Maybe your relationship is more
likely to succeed if you're in different project groups."</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Analogies

<ul>
<li>Like roommates - not everyone you're good friends with is someone
you want to be roommates with</li>
<li>"In 2011, a divorce did happen, but that meant someone
<em>transferred out of the program</em>."</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Choosing a Project</h2>

<p>"<em>It's fun to brainstorm and come up with ideas.</em>" -A. Voigt</p>

<ul>
<li>Evaluate ideas wrt. personal goals for the design project

<ul>
<li>Research?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>It's fun to brainstorm and come up with ideas

<ul>
<li>Take notes; record all ideas when brainstorming</li>
<li>Don't get stuck in this stage forever</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Scope: build MVP (Minimal Viable Product) first, then iterate

<ul>
<li>est. 40 hrs/person for MVP -- any more and it's not minimal enough</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Having A Customer</h2>

<p>"<em>I think Paul Thagard is a good customer.</em>" -D. Rayside</p>

<ul>
<li>Start looking for an external customer early

<ul>
<li>"Good" client defines requirements, will use product (daily?)</li>
<li>Regular (daily/weekly) meetings can be motivating</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Be clear about expectations, esp. intellectual property, money,
legal

<ul>
<li>Policy 73</li>
<li>"Things get more complicated when you go outside the university."</li>
<li>Template IP agreements coming: P. Ward, VeloCity/SSO</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Project Management</h2>

<p>"<em>There <strong>will</strong> be arguments over decisions.</em>"</p>

<ul>
<li>Divide project into small and tangible chunks</li>
<li>"Feature freezes" for bug fixing</li>
<li>Have meaningful commit messages</li>
<li>Commit after each bug/feature, NOT after three and a half weeks</li>
<li>Prioritize: requirements tend to slip each week</li>
<li>Work over co-op is challenging after 9-hr work day

<ul>
<li>Groups that -do- work on FYDP during work term reported feeling
ahead of the game</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Consider selecting a team leader
(<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benevolent_Dictator_for_Life">BDFL</a>)</li>
<li>Get mobile apps into market ~1 month early to get feedback</li>
</ul>


<h2>Technical Infrastructure</h2>

<p>"<em>I <strong>will</strong> punish you for not having an automated build system.</em>"
-D. Rayside</p>

<ul>
<li>Bug Tracking: GitHub</li>
<li>Automated Build Systems</li>
<li>Test Harnesses / Unit Tests

<ul>
<li>good for refactoring</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>bring in <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000043.html">Joel
test</a></li>
<li>Domains

<ul>
<li>Do NOT use GoDaddy</li>
<li>Alternatives: NameCheap, Netfirms, Dyn</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Email

<ul>
<li>Google Apps: Free Tier</li>
<li>Use project-specific email when signing up for stuff

<ul>
<li>Avoids single point of failure (if you get hit by a bus and
everything is attached to your email address...)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Web Hosting

<ul>
<li>Cloud/VPS: AWS, Prgmr, Linode

<ul>
<li>Skills and Flexibility</li>
<li>OpenBSD?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Elastic Beanstalk, App Engine, Heroku

<ul>
<li>Vendor lock-in</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>SSL

<ul>
<li>Free certs from cert.startcom.org, www.startssl.com</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Be wary with ORM limitations: raw SQL is occasionally better

<ul>
<li>Does your ORM do <em>LEFT SEMI JOIN</em>?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Miscellaneous</h2>

<p>"<em>Here's a story - an unprofessional story in a sense - of a wiki that
lived on a machine in someone's office. And that hard drive died.</em>"
-D. Rayside</p>

<ul>
<li>D. Rayside intends to add "a bit of structure" to provide "social
motivation" to get students to work on the design project

<ul>
<li>Each team submits lines and hours, and we take the top and bottom
and annoit them as "professionals" and "mediocrity"</li>
<li>"I want to keep the data in a programatically convenient form."</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Historical artifacts available from 2012 class

<ul>
<li>None from prior years</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>We will likely have D. Rayside for SE 490</li>
<li>The ultimate deadline is on symposium day at the end of 4B</li>
<li>Be enterprising, practical, creative, risk-taking, innovative,
relevant</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
